<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Envy's bitterness corrected with the rod of shame: Or, An answer to a book lately published by Richard Haines (a person withdrawn from) entituled, New lords, new laws; wherein is shewed such an image of envy, as in late ages have not appeared, by his heaping up false accusations, and abusive expressions to a great number, with malicious insinuations, thereby to provoke (if possible) the civil magistrate to have suspitious thoughts of the innocent, with a great out-cry of usurpation and tyranny, proved to have no other foundation but his own evil imaginations, and so, neither lords, nor new laws. : Wherein also the several persons therein accused, are in righteousness quitted, to the shame of the accuser. / By Matthew Caffyn ...</title>
            <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C206A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173316</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097589</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171201</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171201)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2567:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Envy's bitterness corrected with the rod of shame: Or, An answer to a book lately published by Richard Haines (a person withdrawn from) entituled, New lords, new laws; wherein is shewed such an image of envy, as in late ages have not appeared, by his heaping up false accusations, and abusive expressions to a great number, with malicious insinuations, thereby to provoke (if possible) the civil magistrate to have suspitious thoughts of the innocent, with a great out-cry of usurpation and tyranny, proved to have no other foundation but his own evil imaginations, and so, neither lords, nor new laws. : Wherein also the several persons therein accused, are in righteousness quitted, to the shame of the accuser. / By Matthew Caffyn ...</title>
                  <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Haines, Richard, 1633-1685. --  New lords, new laws, or, A discovery of a grand usurpation.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Discipline.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171201:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENVYS BITTERNESS CORRECTED WITH THE ROD of SHAME: OR, An Anſwer to a Book lately Publiſhed by <hi>Richard Haines</hi> (a perſon withdrawn from) Entituled, <hi>NEW LORDS, NEW LAWS;</hi> Wherein is ſhewed ſuch an Image of Envy, as in late Ages have not appeared, by his heaping up falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, and abuſive Expreſſions to a great number, with Malicious Inſinuations, thereby to provoke (if poſſible) the Civil Magiſtrate to have ſuſpitious thoughts of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, with a great Out-Cry of Uſurpation and Tyranny, proved to have no other Foundation but his own evil Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and ſo <hi>Neither LORDS, Nor New LAWS.</hi> Wherein alſo the ſeveral Perſons therein Accuſed, are in Righteouſneſs quitted, to the Shame of the Accuſer. By <hi>Matthew Caffyn</hi> of <hi>Horſham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>He that is firſt in his own cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his Neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 8.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Neither can they prove the things whereof they accuſe me,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:171201:2"/>
            <head>A WORD, to his WORD, To the Ingenious and Learned Peruſers.</head>
            <p>WHereas <hi>Richard Haines</hi> is pleaſed to ſuggeſt, that neither Nature nor Education had furniſhed him with Arts and Accompliſhments neceſſary for ſuch publick undertakings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon intreats their favourable conſtruction in the enſuing leaves, as often as they found him unskilful in Language or methodical Order. I would only ſay, that Perſons of an ordinary Capacity may eaſily judge him a man ſomewhat wanting ſimplicity and ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart in ſo ſpeaking; for that 'tis ſo well known, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by many, (himſelf being the cauſe thereof) that another perſon (whom both Nature and Education hath furniſhed with Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments neceſsary for ſuch publick Concerns) did frame his matter into that form and manner of language wherein it now appears, and is ſent forth to publick View.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171201:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Envy's Bitterneſs Corrected with the Rod of Shame:</hi> OR, An Anſwer to a Book lately publiſhed by <hi>Richard Haines,</hi> (a perſon withdrawn from) Entituled, New <hi>LORDS,</hi> New <hi>LAWS.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving peruſed the Book, entituled, <hi>New Lords, New Laws,</hi> ſubſcribed by <hi>Richard Haines,</hi> and obſerving the many reproaches, falſe accuſations, and abuſive expreſſions therein contained, and more eſpecially thoſe his malicious inſinuations, whereby he (as one much out of the fear of God, and greatly in the Spirit of Envy) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to ſuggeſt amongſt the Sons of Men that we are, but eſpecially my ſelf, (in and about our proceedings againſt him in way of Excommunication) Enemies to his Majeſties Laws, and Royal Prerogative (the contrary whereof, I doubt not but through grace, will appear:) having (I ſay) obſerved theſe things, was made to remember <hi>SimeoNs</hi> diſcription of envy (as may be read in the Book of the twelve <hi>Patriarks</hi>) after this manner. Envy (ſaith he) <hi>maketh a mans Soul to grow Savage, breedeth War in his thoughts, ſetteth his Blood on fire, driveth him out of his wits, and ſuffereth no reaſon to bear ſway or rule, maketh his body ghaſtly, pineth away at the proſperity of the perſon envied, and is always egging him to ſlay the ſame.</hi> For (as ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>the wrath of man worketh not the righteouſneſs of God.</hi> Now the many bitter, and dreadful ſtreams that flow from this fountain of malice and envy, you, in the enſuing diſcourſe, are deſired
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:171201:3"/>to obſerve; And firſt touching his too common Language, how bitter, how unſavory, how unbecoming any profeſſor, but more eſpecially ſuch as excel in knowledg of the Fathers will, even, that every idle word muſt be accounted for at laſt, who yet ſhall not only ſo do, but as it were out-ſtrip therein the deeds of the wicked! as this following Catalogue of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, gathered out of his Book, do plainly demonſtrate. To wit, <hi>Vſurper, Tyrant, Idol, new Lord, Bell, infallible Apoſtle, Idol-God, Seducer, Deceiver, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtart Lord Eccleſiaſtick, narrow Throated tender-Conſcience of his Lordſhips grace, Pope-ſhip, that, had he the priviledge of a torturing Inquiſition, would ſeverely deal with all that ſhould dare oppoſe him, a ſecond Popiſh infallibility, Tyrannical cruelty, Deotriphes.</hi> As touching the Congregation (whom but a while ago, with my ſelf, was highly eſteemed by him) he now ſaith, that they are ſuch <hi>whoſe zeal hath been much more fervent for the adoration of their Idol, than for God, whoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and practices</hi> (meaning I ſuppoſe, with reſpect to their dealing with him) <hi>are Popiſh and Antichriſtian, Confederats with a uſurping Tyrant, whoſe actions he ſuppoſeth are like the hair-brained Proclamations of John of Leyden, or the extravigances of a Popiſh Bull,</hi> and in one of his Letters ſent to <hi>(C.G.)</hi> ſaith, That they are the ſeat of the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Now that ſuch Language ſhould proceed out of the mouths of men always accuſtomed thereunto, is no marvel; (though every where to be lamented) but that it ſhould proceed out of the mouth of a profeſſor, and not only ſo but againſt his Friends, but awhile ago by him eſteemed moſt beloved bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, is more than a little to be admired, yet not ſo much as when his reproachful words ſhall be conſidered in conjunction with his malicious deſigns, no leſs threatning than ruin and deſtruction, and that to his late-eſteemed (and to uſe his own words. Page 2.) <hi>Most worthy and most faithful Brother:</hi> whereby juſt occaſion is given for conſiderate perſons to determin, that ſomething more than ordinary, gave being to this height of envy, at which root, (as the undoubted cauſe thereof, and preceding the controverſie about his Patent too) our friends at <hi>London</hi> ſtruck at, when by mutual conſent on his, and my part, the matter was to be revealed (without which, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with other matters, is queſtionleſs no more in order to communion than the plucking of branches, while the bitter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171201:3"/>root, I mean his envy againſt me, and others, as ſome think, for my ſake remains) but how this then was prevented by his means (contrary to earneſt expectations) friends may well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, though the making that private caſe from being in ſome kind a publick caſe was not prevented; for which he may complain of no mans folly more than his own, for hereby and other ſuch like unwary proceedings of his elſewhere, the caſe by me only hinted at, when thoughts of preſenting it to the Churches conſideration was entertained, (the only Judg of ſuch caſes as many believe) though from a holy deſign the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to regain him, afterwards to the contrary reſolved, there being for other cauſes ſufficient ground to withdraw from him: the caſe, (I ſay, to that degree private) is now become, and by ſome called; <hi>The private publick caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince he pretends, and ſtill would lay the cauſe of his ſo great diſpleaſure upon injuſtice, ſuppoſedly, acted on our parts towards him in the caſe of his Excommunication; though that was no preventing cauſe of his expected gain by his Patent, thereby to enrage him; nor could (in likely-hood) the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his, ſuppoſed, illegal Excommunication, (eſpecially when good reaſon according to the common belief of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) ſo plainly teſtifieth our deſign therein to be good) provoke to ſuch a height of malice, for that we have no preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (I ſuppoſe) of like malice, in the whole Nation, amongſt the many excommunicated perſons that are there, who doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs are as ſtrongly perſwaded as he can be (at leaſtwiſe many) that their Excommunication was unreaſonable and unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: but ſince (I ſay) he otherwiſe pretends, the matter of his Book is now to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>And firſt that preſſing neceſſity that (he ſaith) engaged him to this publication, is worthy obſervation, namely, <hi>that our proceedings againſt him did appear to him no leſs than uſurped Authority;</hi> to which I ſay, that had our proceedings againſt him been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his repreſentation thereof in all points, ſome reaſon he had to manifeſt (at leaſtwiſe) ſome diſlike, but foraſmuch as the enſuing account will hereunto be a reſolution, I ſhall not here inſiſt thereon.</p>
            <p>As to his ſecond reaſon for publication, to wit, <hi>his care to preſerve the truth, and the profeſſors thereof from reproachful abuſes and cenſures.</hi> I anſwer, that to us 'tis unknown that any reproach
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171201:4"/>was upon the account, of the method and manner of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, neither indeed could it be, for that perſons not in Communion with us, were ignorant thereof, if he have repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it after that abuſive manner (as he hath in his Book) to ſome, and thereby ſome reproachful words have been raiſed, that lieth at his door, and not at ours; and as to the ground and cauſe of our proceedings with reſpect to his coveting the Patent, nothing is more apparent than that we are (amongſt men) very generally juſtified, and rendred is doing well and wiſely therein; but, alas, how may the Reader be convinced that his plea to preſerve the truth from reproach, is a candid and real plea? ſince he hath not ceaſed to do, and juſtifie that which is ſo great an occaſion of reproach, and ſo generally too, as the like in our time ſcarce have been, ſo many perſons, in ſo many places being concerned therein.</p>
            <p>As to his third Reaſon for publication, to wit, <hi>becauſe all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition and advice had been diſregarded, and that from a full meeting, and</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>of the moſt eminent in London, to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min that caſe.</hi> I anſwer, that all this ſplendid ſhew of rejecting Counſel when ſtated in plainneſs, was no more than that ſome few friends at <hi>London,</hi> (willing to make an Aſſay for Peace, for ſome good reaſons expreſſed in their Letter to me, wherein only I was by a Friend or two deſired to come up) did appoint to meet at a Coffey-Houſe, and this without the leaſt advice or conſent from us, which ſurely muſt have been as one thing neceſſary in order, to the meetings Authority to determin as he would ſuggeſt, the which was ſo far from their intention, as that plainly and publickly they declared the contrary, as may very well be remembred; yet (by this) my meaning is not that therefore the counſel and advice of any men fearing God may be rejected, but rather (as a truth nothing to be doubted of) to follow the Souls conviction of truth, by what means ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever convicted; now this appointment, by thoſe few Friends, being known, ſeveral others came, who, I ſuppoſe, had a mind thereunto; at which place, <hi>Mr. G.</hi> by his deſire was (and ſome others of the ſame differing perſwaſion from us) who moſt principally ſpake, and adviſed in the caſe, as being (with others) not ſatisfied that he deſerved ſuch blame as we thought him worthy of, though they readily believed (with us) that his undertakings were of an ill report, and of a goſpel-diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171201:4"/>Nature. And whereas he ſaith, that ſome have declared that they do not <hi>owne our London-Friends, nor regard their Counſel;</hi> for the rectifying thoſe miſtakes, that, very poſſibly, may from thence ariſe, all may know (if any there be that know not) that there is the ſame concord between them and us, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Communion, and that not only with ſome, but with all the Elders and Congregations in <hi>London,</hi> as was before this difference happened, too evident to be denyed. As for <hi>Mr. G.</hi> and thoſe Friends of the ſame perſwaſion with him, 'tis indeed true that we, and as true that others in City and Country as well as we, have for ſome well known cauſe, forborn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating together at the Table of the LORD with them.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>our Publication of his Excommunication to the World within three days after 'twas done, and that to them that hated him most,</hi> is pretended by him to be the original cauſe of this publication. My anſwer is, that neither within three days, nor any day ſince did I to thoſe perſons open my mouth thereabouts, what others have done, certainly I know not, but this I know, that ſince our with-drawment from him was (partly) to preſerve the truth, and the profeſſors thereof from reproach, the divulging thereof was not ſo improper as he may conceive.</p>
            <p>And whereas he further adds, that when he was at the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral meeting at <hi>London,</hi> in order to make his appeal there, <hi>I hindered the determination thereof,</hi> when as (he ſaith) <hi>I promiſed to do what I could to have it determined there.</hi> I anſwer, firſt you may obſerve that (as himſelf confeſſeth in his Book) I ſeeing him there, did move his requeſt to the aſſembly, whereupon, after ſome little debate about the matter, a very fair and unanimous reſult was given, that they, by reaſon of an agreement formerly made, could not then hear his caſe; but if he would firſt make his appeal to the <hi>Country</hi> aſſociation, or quarterly meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereunto he belonged, and they, by reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of the caſe, or difference thereabouts, could not decide the matter; that then they would readily hear it: nor could he reaſonably miſtruſt this reſult as proceeding from his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Enemies, becauſe they were generally ſilent in the caſe; and when his motion was thus ſtopped, by vertue of that afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid agreement, I then offered my willingneſs to condeſcend (beyond what is common) namely, that, if he would accept
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171201:5"/>of the aſſemblies advice by making application to the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly meeting, I ſhould be willing that the preſent Aſſembly ſhould chooſe out ſix men or more, who with the quarterly meeting in the <hi>Country,</hi> ſhould be the only Judges of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter depending betwixt us, and that I and the congregation would not be concerned, ſave only to give evidence: all which he very obſtinatly refuſed; whereupon ſome motion was made by ſome one or more about chooſing ſome certain perſons out of the Aſſembly, to whom the caſe might be referred, to which was replied by ſome of the meeting, that the matter concerned the Congregation, and they were not preſent; and that I ſaid any ſuch thing, I am not certain; if I did, 'twas true; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he may not think that the Aſſembly would have impoſed any ſuch thing upon them, if they had been preſent; what may be done by mutual conſent, is another caſe; nor may it be thought ſtrange that I did not engage them to be there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of our former agreement, whereby I well knew that many caſes upon that account had been refuſed; nor may he think that Churches are obliged to follow the motions of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated perſons whither they pleaſe; but rather (as ſome think) that the Church appealed unto, ſhould (if they ſee cauſe to ſtir) by their repreſentatives come to the Church, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whoſe actions the appeal is made, but by this my account aforeſaid, I do not thereby mean that in purſuance of ſuch a promiſe as he ſpeaketh of, I did what I did in and about his caſe, for no ſuch promiſe can I remember, nor do I in the leaſt incline to believe that I did ſo ſpeak, and have forgot it, (though in many caſes that is probable) becauſe I certainly know (and in the ſame page himſelf confeſſeth) that I told him, as I, with another Friend, <hi>(J. S.) Who is ready to witneſs the truth thereof)</hi> ſat with him in his own Parlour by the Fire; I ſay, that I told him of this our agreement, whereby (to uſe his own words) <hi>he was made by me, and others, to doubt that his cauſe could not be heard;</hi> probably if the whole Aſſembly had preſſed for the hearing thereof (as they wholly declined it) I ſhould not have endeavoured to have hindered it, both parties being there. The caſe then being thus, why he ſhould further charge me (as he doth) <hi>for wanting civil honeſty in not telling him before to prevent trouble and unneceſſary charges,</hi> I verily know not.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:171201:5"/>
            <p>And whereas he rejected the general Aſſemblies Advice, firſt to Appeal to ſome Country and Quarterly Meeting, he would very willingly juſtifie the ſame, by ſaying, (<hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi>) That <hi>in ſome reſpects they were inferior to me, and that I was adered, and esteemed by many of them.</hi> To which I anſwer, that were I ſuch a perſon as he now repreſents me to be, 'twere not likely I ſhould be thus eſteemed, or doth he think that they are all in the dark, and he only in the excellent diſcovering light, while a Reviler, a Reproacher, and falſe accuſer of his Brethren, but how ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable is it that while he in his fourth Page of his Epiſtle repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents <hi>me to be thus eſteemed and adored by the Country Congregations,</hi> in the ſixth Page of this Epiſtle, he in anſwer to ſome (I know not who) that ſtrange why he doth not withdraw from the Baptized Congregations, ſaith, <hi>That he knows not any other Congregation of that perſwaſion, corrupted with thoſe Errors, but that their actions and converſations are according to their Profeſſion,</hi> If ſo, why then would he not (I pray) make his Appeal to ſome of them according to the Aſſemblies advice? but 'tis happened to him according to what is written, <hi>where envying is, there is confuſion, as well as every evil work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, whereas the Countries motion and ſtiring againſt his coveted Patent, and that with more then a little pains and charge, while from Town to Town, and from one Gentlemans houſe to another, perſons did Ride up and down, in obtaining their Hands ſubſcribed againſt him, by which, as alſo the plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Counſel eminent in Law, the Patent before the Lord Keeper was threw out, whereas (I ſay) the Countries Motion thus againſt him, but eſpecially their Prevailing, ſeems to bare hard againſt him, not only as an Infallible Teſtimony that his deſigne proved ſcandalous, and of an ill report, but that alſo it ſeems to render the reaſonableneſs pretended by him for his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, queſtionable; he thereupon (I fear) have deſperately lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out into falſe accuſations, in order to the helping his cauſe, namely, in publiſhing (<hi>pag.</hi> 3.) That <hi>I and my Confederates did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port (whereby the Country was provoked to Conſpire againſt him) that his deſign by his Patent was to hinder Perſons from cleanſing Clover as well as Non-ſuch, and that other perſons had made diſcovery thereof before him, then which nothing is more evidently falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>We the Congregation Aſſembled, and judging our ſelves concerned, do hereby declare, that we never heard our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171201:6"/>
               <hi>Caffyn</hi> at any time either plainly declare, or by any hints ſuggeſt ſuch an intention to be in <hi>R. H.</hi> concerning Clover; nor did we at any time believe, and thereby declare to others, any ſuch thing: nor do we know that our Brother <hi>Caffyn,</hi> or any Confederates, (as he ſpeaketh of) that did believe, and ſo report that other perſons had made the diſcovery before him, thereby to provoke thoſe perſons at the firſt to conſpire againſt him, for the moſt diſcourſe of that kind coming to us from perſons not in the Profeſſion, (whether true or falſe, we cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knew not) was after thoſe perſons had actually conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as he calleth it) againſt him, as is eaſie to be demonſtrated.</q>
            <p>But whereas the falſeneſs of this charge cannot appear to the Reader, but upon his prefering my Teſtimony in conjunction with the Congregations Teſtimony, before his bare and ſingle Teſtimony, in a ſtate of apparent Envy, and Excommunication, (though that be a caſe of much clearneſs and plainneſs) I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am made willing here to preſent an accuſation of his, for nature and kind ſuch, as that many perſons, in many places, upon their own knowledge, may determine the ſlanderouſneſs thereof, theſe lines of his, I ſuppoſe, not likely to be read in many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, either in City or Country, but where either my words ſometimes there, or my practiſe there, or agreements made by me, and others to the contrary there, or however ſome that well knew my judgment to the contrary there, may teſtifie againſt him as a falſe accuſer therein; his accuſation is, (<hi>pag.</hi> 12.) <hi>That by my Law I maintaine that when a Widdow or Maid ſhall Marry with one not in fellowſhip, ſhe ſhall be accuſed as an Offendor, and no humility to be accepted of, but Excommunicated ſhe muſt be, and ſhe not to be forgiven to the hour of Death, except they part, or he be converted to them, but in the mean time ſhe is to be adjudged to live in fornication, and ſo their Children are Baſtards.</hi> Now, what ſhew in Reaſon he had thus to ſpeak, I can by no means conceive, there having been at no time, either while he was with us, or ſince he was ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from us, any perſon ſo Excommunicated here, or by me, as an inſtrument elſewhere; nor did I ever believe any ſuch thing, that perſons ſo Married, might be ſeperated (as he inſinuates) nor that they were to be adjudged ſuch as lived in Fornication, ſo as that no humility might be accepted of, nor that their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were Baſtards, the contrary being moſt evident from the actual receiving and embracing ſeveral, in ſeveral places, upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171201:6"/>their profeſſed humility for their ſo doing; and whereas he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth them at <hi>London,</hi> as men of other Principles; they of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> can tell him that I was one of the Aſſembly at <hi>London,</hi> where theſe things were treated of, and well do I remember that I then wrote the agreement, in contradiction to the thoughts of ſome few that way inclined, as by him is mentioned: If from ſome reports theſe things have been ſuggeſted to him, (though not likely) why did he not at ſome time ſpeak of it? and not thus to have as it were ſold us into the hands of Scorners: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if it were true, (as nothing is more falſe) what is it ſo great an evil now, and thought worthy thus to be publiſhed, and no evil at all when he was in fellowſhip with us? for he never ſhewed the leaſt diſlike as (I know) to our Principles in this caſe. Oh! what will not Envy do? well ſaid the wiſe Man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.18. <hi>There is that ſpeaketh like the piercings of a Sword, but the Tongue of the wiſe is health.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We the Congregation, do hereby teſtifie and declare, that neither we with our Brother</hi> Caffyn, <hi>did after the aforeſaid manner Excommunicate any perſon at any time, nor did we ever hear him, either publickly or privately, teach any ſuch Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if <hi>R. Haines,</hi> (too regardleſs of Gods honour, and the Goſpels credit) ſhall thus, even to the knowledge of moſt of you, publiſh falſhoods, what credit and eſteem his bare ſayings, and naked ſuggeſtions may juſtly require, when they ſhall lie in the ballance together with our Teſtimonies to the contrary, let the judicious judge.</p>
            <p>The next thing in the way conſiderable is, our proceedings at the Quarterly Meeting, where we thought it expedient to offer to our Brethren, the Strangers, the caſe of <hi>(R. H.)</hi> his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting the Patent, that in the mutual conſideration thereof we might the better be confirmed what to do, whom we found in like manner diſſatisfied, they not knowing how his caſe might be juſtified, ſo as that the truth might be juſtified, and quitted from reproach: alſo as touching my calling the laws of men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt (as he ſaith there I did) and ſaying, what have we to do with the Laws of men? whereby (as one much beneath not only Chriſtianity, but even moral civility) he would have the reader to ſuppoſe that I am a man (as his Title Page declareth) <hi>Acting grand <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation in contempt of the good Laws, and Royal Prerogative of his Majeſtie.</hi> In anſwer thereunto, firſt let it be obſerved, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171201:7"/>this ſo confident a Publiſher of a matter ſo criminal, if true in his Sence, was not (as himſelf ſaith) at this meeting himſelf to heare it; he being about thirty or forty miles of; and ſo this his publication (as to this particuler) is only from information, and with no ſmall probability from one then preſent, who bares much of his envious image, and alſo out of communion for want of a good converſation.</p>
            <p>How much therefore beneath the actings of men (qualified with but common honeſty) he in this caſe appears, is not hard to conceive; for that he neither conſidered how probable it was that the informer might be miſtaken in his relation (a caſe very common among men, where nothing of prejudice rules, but much more where 'tis manifeſt) nor yet conſidered the great unliklyhood of the truth thereof that might very eaſily to him appeare from the expreſſions themſelves; which ſuppoſeth no leſs then my paſſing judgment againſt the Laws of men in general as unjuſt, which cannot rationally be thought to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of the mouth of the greateſt Fifth-Monarch in the world, (much leſs from him that is a Writur, a Preacher, and a diſputer againſt them; for tis not the injuſtice of the civil Laws of Nations that by them is ſo much oppoſed (however not in ſuch a general ſence as envy here repreſents me) as the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe by them ſuppoſed in ſome perſons that have to do in the execution of thoſe Laws; however right well do we know, and accordingly have we always declared, that by the juſtice &amp; equity of the civill Laws, our common Rights, Privilegdes, and properties are preſerved from ſuch as are unreaſonable; as alſo our lives ſecured from the hands of blood-thirſty men: nor ſince reaſon will not permit the entertainment of ſuch thoughts may any one think that the Laws of men, in relation to Patents, were generally by me condemned as unjuſt, for that frequently I have ſaid, and do now again ſay, that for Perſons to have Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in ſeveral caſes, as they may be circumſtanced, is both legal and reaſonable, as many can teſtifie; his frequent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore repreſenting me an Enemy to Patents (generally) and the Kings Prerogative thereabouts, is altogether groundleſs and unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Nor is there ſo much in that Queſtion, <hi>what have we to do with the Laws of men?</hi> (though that it was ever ſo ſpoken I know not) if righteouſly conſidered, the outmoſt thereof being no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171201:7"/>more then that we, apprehending the Laws of the Goſpel, to forbid this his Goſpel diſhonouring Patent, did not think our ſelves concerned in our Congregational affairs with the Laws of Men, if they did allow it: No more ſurely did <hi>Paul</hi> judge the <hi>Corinthians</hi> concerned with the civil Laws of the Country where they lived, and therefore (knowing the Goſpel rules would not allow them in the apprehenſion of wrong and treſpaſſes received in civil things, to do what the civil Laws would allow them to do) ſaid, <hi>Dare any of you, having a matter against another, go to Law,</hi> (that is, with their Brethren) as if it had been ſaid, you may by no means ſo do, for that you have another Rule from Chriſt to act by, as you are Members of the Church of Chriſt: what have you to do with the Laws of Men, thereby to trouble and vex your Brethren withal? yet might not any therefore think (though <hi>R. H.</hi> think ſo of me) that <hi>Paul</hi> was an Enemy to the civil Laws of the Country, nor to the Prerogative of the King, or Governour that made them: but ſuch have been my Doctrine where ever I came, with reſpect to Chriſtian obligations, <hi>To be ſubjest to the higher Powers, and to obey every ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake;</hi> ſuch alſo have been my publick Reaſonings, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conferences in divers places, in oppoſition to that ſpirit that deſpiſeth Dominion, ſuch hath been my forwardneſs, not only that <hi>Feſtus</hi> his civil Laws ſhould be obſerved, but that his perſon alſo ſhould be honoured, <hi>as most noble Feſtus,</hi> though as to mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, he be found telling <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>he is beſides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> yea, and ſuch have been in that caſe my Principles many years ago publiſhed in Print (which is yet viſible) ſubſcribed by me and many others, as that I do not ſuppoſe the unworthy inſinuations of a man thus over-maſtered with the ſpirit of Envy, will gain credit among many, if any.</p>
            <p>At this our Meeting, 'tis true, that in anſwer to a queſtion propoſed, ſome diſcourſe we had touching ſuch as ſhould make oppoſition againſt, and condemn the Church, in abeting, and juſtifying a perſon that ſhould by ſuch means be the occaſion of ſo much diſhonour to the Truth, but that I, by any <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Authority or Threats, conjured them to do my will</hi> (as he abuſively ſpeaks) by me is denied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neither do we the Congeregation know any ſuch thing, nor do we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that our Brethren the ſtrangers, if they ſhall be enquired of can teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any things of that Nature, no nor any thing tending to the contempt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171201:8"/>of his Majeſties Laws, or Royal Prerogative as by him is ſuggeſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it true that Patents was at this meeting rendred odious (as he would ſuggeſt) nor that I could as freely have fellowſhip with an Idolator, or an unclean perſon, as with a man that ſhould obtain a Patent, the truth being only, that his Patent in that particuler caſe, thus circumſtanced, neither I nor others could bare with, no more then other publick tranſgreſſions.</p>
            <p>Nor had he reaſon to ſay, <hi>That I with the advice of my adherents, did all this Meeting enact by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Authority, that none might buy or ſell for him:</hi> ſince no more is true of that Nature, ſave only that (in anſwer to one enquiring, whether it might be ſafe for him to be concerned, if deſired in ſome one particular place, to Trade in Buying and Selling that particular Seed for him, who was thus defamed, cenſored, and evilly ſpoken of upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) ſome, very few, did declare their preſent thoughts that it was not; but that there was an agreement of the Aſſembly, neither I nor others do know, and that he that reported this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto <hi>R.H.</hi> was (in the beſt ſence imaginable) miſtaken, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by our peaceable communion with his Servants that we well know Trades in Buying, Selling, cleanſing, if not alſo Buying the ſame Seeds for him; and yet may this be publiſhed as a ſign that his Brethren (but a while ago, Beloved, and moſt faithful Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) are now like unto the Antichriſtian Beaſt: Ah poor peice of Envy!</p>
            <p>The next thing conſiderable, is that <hi>R. H.</hi> being formerly by ſeveral Friends perſwaded to deſiſt his deſign, and he not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſwaded, was afterwards deſired to come to a Church Meeting to treat with our Friends thereabouts, before he did endeavour the accompliſhment of his deſign, the which alſo being obſtinately refuſed by him, ſaying, that we had nothing to do to meddle in ſuch matters, and ſo he proſecuting effectually his deſign, at a Meeting ſome time after, we deſired him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, he accordingly did appear, where, ſaith he, we excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him as a Sinner, <hi>before we had proved him to have Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed any known Law.</hi> In anſwer to which, I ſay, that ſure I am, there was ſome endeavours to convict him of his Sin, and to prove his proceedings unwarrantable, but that what we ſaid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him as good evidence or proof, that he was a perſon ſo offending; I cannot ſay, I rather think that the love of Gain, (ſuppoſedly great) in conjunction with his malice manifeſtly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171201:8"/>great, might blind his eyes: but what is his complaint againſt us herein, more then the complaints of perſons excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted very generally elſewhere.</p>
            <p>And whereas he multiplieth many words of <hi>Lordly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation and Acts of Tyranny,</hi> it may be obſerved that at this meeting there was alſo charged againſt him, his unrighteous dealing with a man about a bargin of Clover, the which then I did and ſtill do believe deſerved blame, and in like manner 'twas judged by the friends, two perſons only excepted, whom I perceived not without ſome doubts, in the caſe, whereupon I condeſcended, and ſo that caſe was omitted; and one of thoſe two perſons was he, of whom he abuſively ſpeaking in his Book, ſaith, that <hi>he would have a man damned for diſpleaſing his Lord Caffyn, rather then for diſpleaſing the moſt High:</hi> which if it had been true that I was thus Idolized by this friend, then ſurely he would have pleaſed me in giving conſent with me and others in the caſe; or if it were true that I were ſuch a Lordly Uſurper (as he would ſuggeſt) ſurely then I ſhould ſome way or other have conſtrained them (or as he ſpeaks) threatned them into a conſent; but while he is thus ſpeaking reproachfully of others, worthy conſideration it is, whether himſelf did not act ſomewhat like an Uſurper, in that he (called there as an offender) would (and it ſeems is yet greatly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended becauſe he could not) ſtop my mouth, (who, as tis well known, was concerned with the Congregation in the Congregations affairs) ſo as that I might not ſpeak in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the matter, till he had firſt diſputed with the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; a ready way for ſeducing Spirits to corrupt aſſemblies, while their Elders ſilently ſtand by, without doing what is their duties to do, even, to defend the flock, if ſuch Uſurping motions of tranſgreſſors might be gratified; and whereas he, ſaith, (pag. 5.) that <hi>he was not ſuffered to treat with any of the Congregation, nor they with him by reaſon of my perpetual interruption, as they if they be honeſt will teſtifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVe the Congregation in the honesty and uprightneſs of our hearts, do teſtifie that</hi> R. H. <hi>did at that meeting reaſon with ſeveral of us, and the only thing denyed by our brother</hi> Caffyn, <hi>and yet no more by him then by our ſelves, was only that unreaſonable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping requeſt of him to stop our brother</hi> Caffyns <hi>mouth as aforſaid, he being willing in himſelf, and we ſeeing no cauſe to the contrary, did many times, as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171201:9"/>well as the reſt of the aſſemblies, offer ſomething to the matter in hand, which he not willing to allow (though it no wayes ſavoured of Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in him deſiring it, but rather of Lordlineſs in him denying it) by that means a deal of obſtruction we meet withal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching our proceedings againſt him, he (the better to render it odious) would have perſons believe that I as a New Lord had made new Laws, called by him alſo a new cheat, namely, <hi>that no perſon may offend the weak brethren in any caſe, or oppoſe his Lordſhips deſign upon pain of Excommunication,</hi> and further, that <hi>when a man ſhall have a lawful right to do any thing in civil matters, if any weak brethren ſhould ſay they were offended with it, it may not be ſuffered.</hi> Pag. 20.21. But as one not content thus far to abuſe us he further inſinuateth, that <hi>if the weak brethren ſhould be offended with his Majeſties Crown,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It being made of Gold (they being already,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>offended with ſuch profeſſors as wear Gold) according to our principle he muſt ſubmit or be dealt with.</hi> Pag. 22. And as if this were not enough to repreſent him weak indeed, while he thus reproachfully ſpeaks of the weak, he further ſuggeſteth that <hi>if a weak brother ſhould cry unto him in a fair for a Ballard, as a fairing, and he ſhould offend him by not anſwering his requeſt, by our Law,</hi> (though in truth it be his own evil imaginations) he ſaith, <hi>thereby he may incur an Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,</hi> Pag. 28. Oh how is Wiſdom turned into folly, and ſtrength into weakneſs! and yet thus (I ſuppoſe) he thinks the matter of his Book will agree with the Title thereof, New Lords, New Laws, and ſo having imagined and framed this image by the art of malice, falls on furiouſly in ſeveral Pages fighting againſt it, as a moſt odious thing, thereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that the Reader ſhould underſtand that we excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated him for offending the weak brethren.</p>
            <q>In anſwer to which we the Congregation, with our brother <hi>Caffyn,</hi> do declare that we never heard of ſuch principles (or practiſes) till his own Book informed us, and therefore we think that they may very well be called, New Laws indeed; our principles being the ſame as when he was amongſt us, the ſame with other Churches, yet never ſuch as did allow that perſons ſhould be Excommunicated for not parting with their lawful rights upon weak brethren, ſaying, they are offended with it, or that required perſons upon pain of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to gratify any ones deſign, or thus to humor the weak
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171201:9"/>brethren offended in any caſe, as he ſuggeſteth; rather have we believed, and ſtill do, that in ſuch caſes the Congregation with her Elders, ſhould endeavour the information of ſuch weak brethren, that they may be more ſtrong, and ſo no longer offended with the Legal proceedings of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and commonly ſuch endeavours prove effectual; and as we are of no ſuch principles, ſo neither are we in our dealings with him, men of ſuch practiſes (as he ſuppoſeth) for that he was Excommunicated to humor and gratifie a company of weak brethren, upon their ſaying they were offended, we do with all clearneſs deny.</q>
            <p>Further, in anſwer, the Reader is to obſerve, that after his Excommunication there was (according to his deſire) a paper ſent him, containing the grounds of our proceedings againſt him, the which (had he dealt uprightly) he ſhould have truly ſtated in his Book, and ſo have endeavoured an anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but to paſs it over in ſilence, without the leaſt making mention of any ſuch Written account from the Church, and yet pretend to give an account of the Churches proceedings againſt him and not only ſo, but in the mean ſeaſon to frame a falſe account of the Churches proceedings, with endeavours to father that upon the Church, and ſo with many ſwelling words from a vain mind, exclaim againſt it, is ſuch a practiſe that is ſeldom heard of, and ſurely never found among any but ſuch as want either wiſdom or ſincerity, or both, what did he think that he being firſt in his own cauſe, ſhould meet with none coming after him to ſearch him out?</p>
            <p>Now that the account given by him is a falſe account, our paper (yet viſible, and that ſince have been read by many) will evidence, (though his ſilence about this paper may ſufficiently Miniſter ſuſpition to the Reader of the trueneſs of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) in all which paper of ours (conſiderably Large) thoſe expreſſions <hi>(to wit, weak brethren)</hi> ſo often named by him, is not once named; nor that a party of weak brethren, being offended with his proceedings, was by others not ſo offended, gratified and humored by caſting him out of the Church, once ſignified; but rather <hi>his reſolutions (againſt all Counſel to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) to perſiſt in his Patent deſign (in conjunction with his unworthy carriage) as a practiſe ſavouring of his preferring the gain of this World, before the honor of the Goſpel, for that thereby Reproach and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171201:10"/>Scandal was brought upon the ſame, whereby the brethren,</hi> (that is, the Congregation, being ſenſible thereof, and not a party only) <hi>was offended,</hi> and yet are that he ſhould ſo ſeek himſelf, his own profit, as no more to regard the obligations of the Goſpel, to avoid ſuch occaſions for the profit of others, that they might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>Though it be alſo true that we were not ſatisfied that his coveting this Patent was upon juſt and lawful grounds, for that nothing (Worthy conſideration) can be pleaded (either as great charge, long ſtudy, or more then common ingenuity) as might with a good conſcience enright him thereunto; and it ſeems the like judgment was made thereof by Counſel (Learned in the Law) Sir <hi>E. T.</hi> and Sir <hi>H. P.</hi> Before the Lord Keeper when the Country appeared at <hi>London,</hi> in their great diſlike and diſcontent about it, with a paper ſubſcribed by the hands of many, as well perſons of quality, as others; where one of the Counſel to evade the cauſe of this deſired Patent, Pleaded (if I miſtake not the information) what (ſaith he) if a man ſhall deviſe a new way to thraſh his Corn, ſhall he therefore have a Patent? ſurely no. However they ſoon made judgment againſt it. Nor did we think it a conſideration void of Reaſon, that he a ſeperate, a profeſſor, ſhould ſeek a Patent in this caſe of Nonſuch, there being Clover (as a preſident) cleanſed after the ſame manner long before; when as no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon out of the profeſſion ſought after a Patent, in the caſe of cleanſing Clover upon the account of being the firſt inventor thereof, though without a preſident; Nor did we think it a vain conſideration that he, having an eſtate conſiderable, and having beſides no ſmall advantage by cleanſing this ſeed, while others cleanſed it as well as he, that he ſhould now, as one not content there with endeavour to graſp all into his own hands, thereby opening the mouths of men to judg him and revile him as a covetous perſon; to the diſhonor of Religion; and indeed how he may be cleered (I cannot tell) from cenſures of that kind, ſince, for the ſake of this wedge of Gold, (cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtanced as aforeſaid) he could part with his brethren (greatly beloved) at once, and not only ſo, but all his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian privil does reſpecting communion; and as he parted with, and loſt theſe on the one hand (with who, upon the like account, beſides a Worldly-minded man would do?) ſo on
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171201:10"/>the other hand he purchaſed infamy to himſelf, and reproach to the Goſpel, and alſo rendred himſelf an occaſion of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to the Sons of Men, while ſometimes upon the road, ſometimes in the Markets, and ſometimes elſewhere, perſons were heard revileing, defaming, and curſing him upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: and what, may ſuch a man that ſhall looſe freely ſo much good, and purchaſe unavoidably ſo much evil, and all for that which is but momentary, yet think himſelf innocent herein? Oh how is it to be lamented!</p>
            <p>The matter then before ſpecified, and thus circumſtanced, being had in publick conſideration, and thoſe wholſome Laws, and Goſpel rules, mentioned and given in charge by the Apoſtle for the prevention of offences, and things of an ill report, being produced, and treated of without offering the leaſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of his mind, he alſo after an unworthy manner cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoring ſome of his brethren in the face of the Aſſembly, we thereupon did judg him as one that did tranſgreſs the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Laws of the Goſpel, and ſo unfit for, and unworthy of, communion. Even, thoſe wholſom Laws (we mean) that the Saints of old (in order to a Goſpel-Honoring converſation) were enjoyned to obſerve; namely, <hi>give none offence neither to the</hi> Jews <hi>nor to the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>nor to the Church of God, and that not only in Eating and Drinking, but whatſoever we did, we ſhould do all to the Glory of God, and not pleaſe our ſelves, nor ſeek our own profit, but the profit of others that might be Saved.</hi> 1 Cor. 10. <hi>and that, if their be any vertue, if there be any praiſe, whatſoever things were lovely and of good report, they ought be the thinking on thoſe things. Phil.</hi> 4.8. Which counſel of the Apoſtle, occaſioned by that forgoing diſcourſe of his, where he chargeth them not to eat that which was lawful to be eaten, when by their ſo doing, others were offended, ſheweth that Chriſtians (in order to their doing all things to the Glory of God) ſhould carefully avoid all occaſions of ill reports, and not give offence to any, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church nor the World, which (as caſes might be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtanced) they might do by the performance of things, (otherwiſe) lawful; provided always that it be conſtrued to ſuch things as are only lawful, and ſo may be done, and not ſuch things as are matter of duty, and ſo muſt be done. The which is readily granted by <hi>Richard Haynes</hi> himſelf, ſaying, Pag. 27. <hi>That if his brother (formerly a Jew) being week dares not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171201:11"/>eat ſwins Fleſh, becauſe once forbiden, and ſo could not have communion with thoſe that he knew did eat it, rather then to offend ſuch a one, he would eat no meat while the World ſtood,</hi> notwithſtanding ſwins Fleſh be lawful in its ſelf to be eaten: ſo that now that which he hath conceived to be our Judgments about the not offending brethren, is no other but that his own opinion and judgment in the ſame caſe of not offending, is come within, even, a hairs breadth of the ſame; the difference being only (as himſelf defines it) that the ſtrong ſhould bare the infirmities of the weak, in all ſuch caſes as have relation to matters of Religion and Worſhip, and not in ſuch civil caſes as his; now ſo much as the eating ſwins Fleſh is contrary to the true Religion and Worſhip of God, in the weak brothers account, more then his coveting this Patent, thereby raking, and graſping in all to himſelf, to the Goſpels reproach, and offence of the brethren, is contrary to the pure Religion and Worſhip of God in our account, (which plainly is that <hi>a man keep himſelf unſpoted from the World</hi>) ſo much and no more is the difference betwixt us. Surely, either none at all, or now if any there be, let it be ſhewn, at leaſtwiſe any requiring ſuch a publication, what, may one weak brother (formerly a Jew) who by reaſon of his weakneſs cannot have communion in caſe ſwins Fleſh be eaten, though the eating thereof be lawful in the ſight of God, may ſuch a one (I ſay) find more favour with <hi>R.H.</hi> then a whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that could not have communion with him in caſe he did proſecute that Patent deſign.</p>
            <p>Nor is that all which may be wondered at, for as in the caſe juſtified by him about the not eating ſwins Fleſh, there is not only a diſproportion betwixt a ſingle perſon offended, and a whole congregation offended; but alſo that the ſingle perſons offence is only injurious unto himſelf without any ſuch atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance as the diſhonor of the Goſpel and injury to others, when as the Congregations offence is attended with (as a main thing too in our account) diſhonour to the Goſpel, and ſo injury to many others, that by that means may ſtumble at the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas he ſuppoſeth injuſtice and cruelty in our proceedings againſt him, for that he conceives he hath not broken neither the Law of God nor man:</hi> doth not <hi>R. Haines</hi> himſelf (that hath laid ſo many grevious complaints againſt us) now plainly juſtifie us?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171201:11"/>by ſaying that he might juſtly be charged as an offender, and (as in his other initance) publikly to be blamed if obſtinate. <hi>Pag.</hi> 27. (as was his caſe) and all this for eating ſwins Fleſh, which to do, is neither the tranſgreſſion of the Law of God nor man; nay, when I enquire whether he doth not now juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us? may I not ſay that he doth (as it were) more then juſtifie us? becauſe in our proceedings againſt him, we were not ſatisfied that his Patent might as lawfully be proſecuted, as ſwins Fleſh might lawfully be eaten: but if to that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction we had attained, yet that pen which hath ſo often and ſo much abuſed us, is made, even, in ſuch a caſe now to juſtifie us. And doth it not then follow that this ſo great a heat of Spirit flows from ſomething beſides and before, the Patent too?</p>
            <p>Moreover, ſince the eating things offered to Idolls, whereby the weak brother is made to tranſgreſs in matters of Religion, is in his account a ſin, and ſuch a ſin too, that deſerves publick rebuke (as he confeſſeth, <hi>Pag.</hi> 27.) is it not as much, if not more deſerving rebuke, this his Patent proceedings (againſt all Counſel and advice to the contrary) ſince not only one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (as he ſtates the caſe thus blamable) but many perſons of the World, is thereby lyable to diſeſteem the true Religion and Worſhip of God, and ſo to harden themſelves in their ſalfe ways of Religion, and ſo many may come to periſh for whom Chriſt died? and therefore if he did eſteem it his lawful right (though one may think it could not be done without ſome doubts, being circumſtanced as aforeſaid) ſhould he not have ſaid (and accordingly done) that, rather then thus to diſhonor the Goſpel, offend the Congregation (and many others) and looſe communion and Chriſtian priviledges, I will not have ſuch a Patent as long as the World ſtands? conſider in the true fear of God.</p>
            <p>Whereas alſo he often affirms, that I ſhould ſay <hi>that Patents were of the Devil.</hi> My anſwer is, that therein (as in many other caſes) he chargeth me falſly. Secondly, <hi>we the Congregation do teſtifie that we never heard our brother</hi> Caffyn <hi>ſo to ſpeak.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>I. H. S. deſired to come to</hi> London <hi>by letter from</hi> R. Haines, <hi>to be a witneſs for him, in which letter he ſeems to ſpeak that I did not only hear brother</hi> Caffyn <hi>ſay that Patents were of the Devil, but alſo that he did declare it at the latter end of his ſentence of Excommunication:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171201:12"/>I. H. S. do hereby declare that I neither heard brother</hi> Caffyn <hi>ſo to ſpeak in the latter end of his ſentence of Excommunication, nor at any other time, ſave only that he at ſome time ſaid, that the evil one put him upon his Patent particularly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas he is pleaſed to call me <hi>great Apoſtle,</hi> and to ſay (in anſwer to a ſuppoſed queſtion. Pag. 43.) <hi>that he was wholly ignorant of my great Office and Authority.</hi> All may know (if any yet do not know) that I never pretended to any thing of that kind, ſave only, as one ſent to preach the Goſpel, but in divers reſpects beneath, and inferior to thoſe ſent out heretofore, as the Apoſtles of Chriſt; and ſo never thought my ſelf to be, nor was thought of others to be, in any other Office, or place of Authority, then thoſe that he again and again appealed unto at the general meeting at <hi>London:</hi> ſo that his pointing at my name particularly, muſt needs flow from a Spirit of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt me particularly; but to be as ſhort as I can, the Reader is to obſerve, That</p>
            <p>Whereas he ſaith, <hi>I think my ſelf equal with</hi> St. Paul. <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. <hi>that I (with the Congregation) do judg that my diſpleaſure is puniſhable (without ſubmiſſion) with no leſs then eternal damnation.</hi> Pag. 15. <hi>That I do contemn the Authority of all above me.</hi> Pag. 18. <hi>That tis not neceſſary in my Government to reprove according to the Scripture Rule, that I have in effect Autherity to do all, to wit, accuſe, judg and condemn.</hi> Pag. 20. <hi>That Whoredom, Fornication, or Idolatry, is rather allowed of then this of the Patent.</hi> Pag. 21. <hi>That if a certain perſon did not confeſs her ſin to me, ſhe muſt (according to my principle) be damned eternally.</hi> Pag. 44. <hi>That I propheſied he ſhould not proſper neither in body nor eſtate,</hi> Pag. 53. <hi>That I question the Kings Royal perogative in ſecular things.</hi> Pag. 41.</p>
            <p>All which, I do hereby ſolemnly proteſt againſt as falſe, and moſt unworthy accuſations, which together with thoſe many before named, and yet is to be named, reſpecting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular caſes yet to be ſpoken to, (paſſing over other things of like kind) will make up ſuch meaſure, as if it were heaped up, preſſed down, and runing over to the great ſhame of the accuſer, and I could wiſh that in the iſſue it might tend to his humiliation, for I do not deſire that the Lord may lay it to his charge.</p>
            <p>Further, he chargeth againſt me <hi>partiality, and conniving at ſin,</hi> &amp;c. And I ſuppoſe none may think (conſidering his ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171201:12"/>great malice againſt me) that he hath left unmentioned any thing that either near, or afar of, lately or formerly, he could meet with, all which fairly anſwered as it reſpecteth me (which to do, through grace, I nothing doubt of) he may reaſonably doubt of ever obtaining his end; for theſe things now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable were, (I ſuppoſe) partly more then ſeven Years ago, and in a nother County, and partly (I ſuppoſe) about five and ſix Years ago, and partly more lately, but all of it (a very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle excepted) while he was in communion with us; nor can he plead (at leaſtwiſe to all) that he was ignorant thereof till now, for in the caſe of the woman dying under blame, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tells the Reader, <hi>Pag.</hi> 44. That 'twas before the difference betwixt us, gathered from a certain diſcourſe between he and I, about which he then ſignified not the leaſt diſlike as I know of, nor at any time ſince, this publication being my firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; and now with no leſs aggravation then an <hi>infallable mark of Popiſh infallibility:</hi> but as touching the matter, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member nothing thereof, ſave only a few words with him in way of ſome miſtruſt of her condition, but that I ſhould, <hi>for want of her confeſſion to me, that I might forgive her my ſelf,</hi> ſay, <hi>that 'twas all one if ſhe did repent of her ſin before ſhe died; and ſo conclude her one that could not enter into the Kingdom, for want of my pardon:</hi> my anſwer is, that I know no ſuch thing as ever ſpoken by me, nor at any time believed, but rather that a ſinner may truly repent before God, and ſo enter the Kingdom, who yet for want of either opportunity, or capaſſity of body, may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs his ſin to the offended; neither is it true that <hi>the controverſie lay between the woman and I,</hi> if thereby he mean, the woman and I only, for ſever I were acquainted therewith, and her Husband the party that was originally offended, (and in ſome reſpects more concerned then ever I was) <hi>who is ready to teſtifie the truth thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas this womans infirmities, reproved by me and others, conſiſted in her two much bitterneſs of Spirit (to the preventing her Husbands will) againſt her Husbands daughter that came home with a great belly (one never in the profeſſion) who charging it upon a certain perſon, he readily confeſſed it, and ſo married her; whereas (I ſay) the caſe was ſo, he having no other cauſe (for doubtleſs if he had, he would even gladly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171201:13"/>have publiſhed it, he concluds the matter, with this queſtion, namely, which of the two, the Mother or the Daughter, I had moſt kindneſs for.</p>
            <p>To which queſtion, and what elſe ſeemingly may look that way elſwhere; I ſhall only ſay, that God Almighty (the alone ſearcher of hearts) knows both his and mine, and if I ſhould be innocent herein, and in all caſes of that kind, (as the Lord knows I am, and ever was, who, ſhould I not be upright herein, would be a ſwift witneſs againſt me) and he ſhould be a man that have been really and foulely guilty in caſes of that kind, and now become an Enemy to him that has told him the truth; how dreadfully, preſumptuouſly, and daringly, doth he thereby Treaſure up Sin and Wrath, againſt the day of Wrath, unleſs timely and greatly he doth repent?</p>
            <p>And whereas he endeavours to render me <hi>partial in my proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt a man and his wife, whom he would ſuppoſe to be my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorite, becauſe my kinſwoman, of whom he ſpeaking,</hi> Pag. 11. <hi>ſaith, that there was a neceſſity of marrying her to ſome body, as if ſhe were with Child by ſome one beſides her eſpouſed Husband.</hi> The caſe was thus, to wit, that theſe perſons being engaged one to the other, did, before publike marriage according to Law, accompany together, the which when they had done, being under trouble of conſcience (as was declared) did voluntarily tell the ſame to a certain friend, from whom I had the Relation, and ſo did immediately take an opportunity to treat with them about their tranſgreſſion, and finding them in a humble fram, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their voluntary acknowledgment, did proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as to any publike rebuke; yet not ſo ſatisfied as to permit either of them to communion, neither have they unto this day: in proceſs of time ſome imaginations did ariſe, and at laſt a diſcovery of the unlawful fact, as that the Goſpel thereby was lyable to be evil ſpoken of, whereupon we at a publike firſtdays-meeting before the Church (and others) bare our teſtimony againſt their ungodly proceedings, without the leaſt ſhew of favour to one more then another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The truth of which we the Congregation do teſtifie. And further ſay, that we never heard before (the fruit of malice diſcovered it) the leaſt word drop from any of our brother</hi> Caffyns <hi>favouring his kinſwomen in that particuler.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:171201:13"/>
            <p>As touching the perſon that did <hi>Beat and</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>Curſe his tired Horſe,</hi> from the relation of which, he further argues <hi>partiality in me;</hi> the Reader is to obſerve, that when I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood there was ſuch a report of this perſon, and that he did deny what was reported, I nevertheleſs did (with another Friend, and two more ſober perſons, not in fellowſhip with us) go to the place where 'twas reported that ſuch words of Curſing was ſpoken, and went from houſe to houſe treating with thoſe that were concerned in the report, and finding them partly to differ in their teſtimony, and partly miſtaken, as in the caſe of his Riding by the Reporters houſe after ſuch a manner as was deſcribed, when as it appeared that he came by the houſe on Foot, driving his Horſe before him, having alſo the teſtimony of one that Rod along the Road with him, not very far from him, when the Reporters ſay he ſpoke thoſe words, who teſtifieth that he heard him ſpeak no ſuch thing: ſo likewiſe ſaith ſome others, who were nigher them then the Reporters, having alſo a paper ſubſcribed by ſeveral of his nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hgburs, that under the greateſt provocations, they never heard him to Curſe nor Swear. We (I ſay) finding the caſe after this manner, though it were true, that two or more did teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie they heard him ſpeak ſuch words, which he did poſſitively deny, we knew not, neither yet do we underſtand that 'twas our duty to condemn him as a Tranſgreſſor in the caſe of Curſing, upon their bare teſtimony, in contradiction to his denyal, and the circumſtances aforeſaid: though as to beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Horſe too furiouſly and intemperately, (yet with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a common flaſh) we did judge him worthy of blame, which he alſo readily confeſſed, neither may <hi>R. H.</hi> think it ſtrange that we receive not the teſtimony of theſe perſons, while we blamed him (as yet we do) for not dealing righteouſly with a poor man about a bargin of Clover, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſed by one ſingle witneſs in the ſame capacity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our blaming him reſpects his own account and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the matter, and not a contrary account from the party concerned, which muſt have been true to have rendred his charge againſt me juſt and reaſonable.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>R. H.</hi> further declareth this perſons unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, (I ſuppoſe more then ſeven years ago) <hi>in ſmiting his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171201:14"/>Apprentice with his Fiſt, he being one that was in the Profeſsion, and conſequently that I was guilty of partiality, in reproveing the ſame but gently and ſparingly:</hi> The Truth is, that at our Meeting, with reſpect to this perſons Tranſgreſſion, after due blame laid upon him, and his ready acknowledgment of the ſame, he was required to go to the people, where in his paſſion, this evil was acted, and there to confeſs his ſin before the people, the which accordingly he did, as may be proved, whether therefore this may evidence my partiality, or his malignity, let the Reader judge.</p>
            <p>Further as to this perſon <hi>R. H.</hi> ſaith, That <hi>in his apprehenſions he ſerveth two Gods, to wit, me as one, and his belly as another God.</hi> From which perſon, (I being not at all concerned in the caſe) take this acount, namely, whereas ſuch and ſo great Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try is ſuggeſted againſt me, <hi>becauſe that I did for ſome time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare eating and drinking with him, and yet nevertheleſs at a certain time did in his Chamber eat and drink with him, and ſaid that I could do ſo again, and ſince have refuſed to eat and drink with him,</hi> from whence I am publiſhed to be guilty of ſo great Idolatry, <hi>p.</hi> 11. theſe are to let the Reader underſtand, that my eating and drinking with him at that certain time, though true in the ſame Chamber, was no more (at leaſtwiſe in my judgment) then what might conſiſt both with my former and latter practiſes; for as he called for ſomething for himſelf, I alſo called for ſomething for my ſelf, and after a diſtinct manner, eat the ſame by my ſelf, though at the ſame Table; which meaſure of diſtinction (however others might do in ſuch a caſe) I thought to agree with my Principles, and therefore ſaid, I could do it again; how then righteouſly it could be ſaid, that I thereby did Idolize Brother <hi>Caffyn,</hi> I verily know not; ſince what I did, was with reſpect to Religion, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his own Relation confeſſeth, I pretended for my ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to accompany with him, but then how I ſhould, either juſtly or reaſonably be thought by him to ſerve my Belly as another God, I neither can underſtand, unleſs by concluding that in eating with him (as aforeſaid) to pleaſe and ſatisfie my Belly, thereby I did what I was perſwaded really and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly I ought not to do, which if ſo he thought, then doth he at once deſtroy the only foundation laid to bare up his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171201:14"/>argument to prove that I did Idolize brother <hi>Caffyn</hi> as another God, to wit, that I did ſorbare eating with him to pleaſe my Idol <hi>Caffyn.</hi> Alas, the darkneſs! Alas, the envy of this poor man! again, how it ſhould be thought that I (or any) ſhould forbare eating and drinking with perſons Excommunicated to pleaſe brother <hi>Caffyn</hi> (which ſuppoſeth him diſpleaſed, if not) I reaſonably cannot think, becauſe 'tis manifeſt (too evidently to be denyed) that ſeveral friends are not (nor ever were) convinced that 'twas their duties to abſtain from eating with ſuch, who nevertheleſs are his well-beloved brethren.</p>
            <p>As touching another perſon whom he repreſents <hi>as one covetous and deceitful, for that he, having ſome-estate, and a good Trade, nevertheleſs covets another, and to maintain the ſame, bound himſelf as an Apprentice to a perſon at ſome distance.</hi> The true Relation whereof (according to my beſt information) is thus, namely, that this perſon having ſerved an Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with a Maſter that was a Taylor by Trade, and alſo ſold Cloath and other things (very common to perſons of that Trade) he in proceſs of time, when Trading for himſelf as a Taylor, did alſo ſell Cloath with other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, during which time, he came to obey the Goſpel, keeping forth his Trade as before, with whom <hi>R. H.</hi> as well as we had communion ſeveral Years, without the leaſt diſlike ſhewed on his part, as ever I heard; and afterwards when he had a Tryal at the Aſſizes about his ſelling Cloath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was (ſerving ſuch a Maſter as aforeſaid, who was preſent to bare his Teſtimoney thereunto) he was (I ſay) juſtified by Law, without the leaſt plea from, or advantage by, his being an Apprentice, which through ſome fear he ſubmitted unto.</p>
            <p>Further, <hi>R. H.</hi> to prove another of his brethren <hi>an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator, and that he was more ready to do the will of his new Lord, then the will of him in Heaven,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>that while he was forward (with others) to Excommunicate him for a pretended ſin against his new Lord, he was backward or neglected his duty towards God, in way of reproving him in another caſe according to what he thought his ſin deſerved.</hi> To which I ſay, that unleſs he had firſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171201:15"/>proved that this perſons not bareing with him, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing with the Church, in their proceedings againſt him, had been becauſe he had ſined againſt me, his New Lord, as he is pleaſed to ſpeak, <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. and not in conſcience of his duty towards God, not only without good, but alſo without ſhew of Reaſon; and ſo I return it back to his ſhame: it being well known that this perſon was ſo far from cenſuring <hi>R. H.</hi> to pleaſe me, as that he was, and yet is, convinced that his coveting this Patent was not only a ſin againſt God, as many believe it, but in ſome reſpect a ſin wherein others do not ſo underſtand it; <hi>and as touching this perſons preſenting</hi> R. H. <hi>his ſin in another caſe after that manner in the meeting, which for ſome time before was acted, and had not been publikely reproved, the</hi> account from the ſaid perſon is, that though it be true, ſometimes he was made to doubt, by Reaſon of his ſmooth words, whether it might deſerve ſuch reproof or no, though at ſome other times again ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that it did, yet that he did readily confeſs his ſin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and not only to him but alſo at the meeting at <hi>London,</hi> where <hi>R. H.</hi> did accuſe him for it, before all the friends then preſent, he did confeſs his fault therein, as I ſuppoſe many do well remember, and as I do well remember: what ſhould be the occaſion of its now publication I cannot interpret, unleſs his continued wrath which worketh not the righteouſneſs of God.</p>
            <p>Further <hi>R. H.</hi> Pag. 15. To prove another of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be an Idolator, tells the Reader <hi>that he at a certain time ſhould ſay, that he could as freely Steal a Horſe as to have a Patent.</hi> From whence he proceeds thus, ſaying, <hi>I pray</hi> Sirs <hi>obſerve how great zeal appears in this deluded perſon for the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the new Laws of this his new Lord, for rather then to ſin against his commands, he had rather ſin against the commands of the most high God. And thereupon concludingly ſpeaks that I muſt needs be their Idol, and ſo calls upon all that are not ſeduced to judg in this matter.</hi> Alas, poor man! will he judg all men are ſeduced that doth not ſee the weight of Truth and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which (by this general appeale) he ſuppoſeth attends him in this his arguing? may it not be thought rather that among even the ſeduced, in many points, and much more
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:171201:15"/>among them that are not ſeduced, that unleſs he had firſt proved that this perſons zeal againſt his Patent had been to pleaſe me (called by him, his New Lord) and not out of conſcience to God, may it not (I ſay) rather be thought, that judgment may be given againſt him, as one Reaſoning without Reaſon?</p>
            <p>But while he thus, either for the want of the Uſe of Reaſon, or uprightneſs, pleads, and all this too from the report of another diſorderly perſon, the perſon concerned ſaith, that his words were only that he thought he could as freely have fellowſhip with him that had ſtolen a Horſe, as with him that ſhould have ſuch a Patent, for that in his account 'twas covetouſneſs: and ſo a tranſgreſſion of Gods Royal Law as ſtealing was.</p>
            <p>And whereas he Further repreſents me <hi>as an actor of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,</hi> becauſe ſometimes I have ſignified my fears, that while perſons are intent upon, and deeply exerciſing their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings about matters of civil controverſies, they may (and ſometimes do) forget their Chriſtian obligations, and ſo misbehave themſelves, as alſo becauſe of the reproaches that probably may come by the diſcontented parties; he might as well have known (however others do) that I have not uſurpingly withſtood ſuch undertakings, for that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral amongſt us have concerned themſelves in making peace between their Neighbours. Where then is <hi>this New Law of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation which he ſpeaks of?</hi> Pag. 8. Doth a mans fears and ſo his particuler diſlike make it a Law? ſurely no. Much leſs <hi>an Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation deſerving ſuch a publication.</hi> But this only more ſhall I ſay to it, that while he ſo much pleads for making peace between men, himſelf is become an enemy to the peace of them that very lately he eſteemed <hi>moſt faithful and beloved brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſaith he alſo, <hi>I reproved him for keeping company with great Perſons.</hi> What, would he hereby, while himſelf inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates into their favour, endevour to caſt me out of their favour, that ſo he might the better accompliſh his malitious deſign? Alas, poor man! I would have him know that in ſimplicity and humility to ſtay upon God, is a more ſurer refuge, and Rock of defence, then by ſinful ſubtilty to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171201:16"/>comply with, and put confidence in the Arm of Fleſh. True it is, that I having ſome fear that he might among ſome perſons of note, take that liberty which would nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be Honourable to the Truth, nor conducable to the good of thoſe he aſſociated with, did cautionally, but not cenſuringly, drop a few words of that import, yet is it no other then what occaſionally many do without gain-ſaying: but the better to effect an evil eye in them againſt me, he (as one little queſtioning whether their prudence would lead them to comply with his reaſonleſs diſtracted thoughts of malice) further imagineth, and ſo declareth that <hi>I had ſome great antipathy againſt ſuch Men;</hi> and, as an agravation of my ſuppoſed tranſgreſſion in thoſe cautionary words, he tells the Reader, that <hi>thoſe perſons of Quality that he aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated with, were ſuch as I well knew to be ſober men of good report, and Favorites to that which is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſay, that if I conjecture aright, whom he means (of which I do not much doubt) then I muſt confeſs that I have no reaſon to gainſay him therein, nor have I any Reaſon to think, that he doth not aſſociate with ſome other perſons of whom thoſe things cannot ſo well be ſpoken. Yet again have I no Reaſon to think that among any of them, ſuch a Spirit of malice againſt profeſſors rules, that leads them to do, not only what he thinks may be done, but what he believes is his duty to do; the which (if I miſtake him not) his words do imploy, which are theſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 37.</p>
            <q>I muſt tell you that according to what is Further my duty I am reſolved to proſecute what I have undertaken againſt him; as though I never knew him, but as an Uſurping Tyrant; and further, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> Pag. 29. Suppoſe the worſt imaginable, to wit, that the civil Magiſtrate for contempt of Authority, ſhould cauſe him to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, can he complain of them, or be offended with me, conſidering what himſelf hath done infinitly beyond it? what? ſhall I puniſh a Man with eternal torments for doing that which is no tranſgreſſion of any known Law, and cry out by reaſon of ſo little pain, as may be over in a quarter of an hour?</q>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:171201:16"/>
            <p>Now, whether he doth not by all this, intimate a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliancy of his Spirit, that I ſhould be proſecuted againſt, even, unto death temporal, who have (as he ſuggeſteth, if any one would believe him) puniſhed him with eternal torments, (though in truth the end of our puniſhing him by the cenſure of the Church is to preſerve him from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment eternal) now whether (I ſay) by all this he do not intimate ſuch a thing, I leave to be conſidered; in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with his Dream, which (were it Divine) ſignifieth no leſs then that he that uſed to ſtand at the upper end of the Table, and perform his Devotion (called by him, in way of reproach, unjuſt Judg or falſe Apoſtle) <hi>was loſt and could no where be found.</hi> Pag. 51. To which I ſhall only ſay, <hi>he that hath a Dream, let him tell his Dream, and he that hath my word, let him ſpeak my word faithfully, what is the chaff to the VVheat ſaith the Lord?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas he ſeemeth to render me as one faulty, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. For that I did not accept of an Offenders confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his offence, <hi>for that 'twas not from the heart, I preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>to know the heart.</hi> My anſwer is, that from what appeared, and doth yet appear, I with the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation were, and yet are, diſſatisfied with that perſon in reſpect of communion: nor is that true touching <hi>this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons committing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in my conceit many Years agoe, the which as 'twas a ſin againſt God I could bare with, but when he had ſinned against my ſelf, then I could not:</hi> For that 'twas no more in my underſtanding, ſave only ſuſpition of ſin from report, and that not ſeveral Years agoe neither (as he ſaith) but ſome late report that lead me, but no Further then into private enquiry; without the leaſt diſcovery on my part to the infamy of either of the perſons concerned. 'Tis true that ſome endevours on my part have been to make diſcovery of ſinners (for which it may be feared that ſome hate me,) but none of the Godly and Truly gratious Souls; but I conſider that <hi>to lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the gate, is no more then what the more worthy Prophets of the Lord have meet with,</hi> Iſa. 29.21. But yet as to the creeping into a Houſe and ſtanding behind a wall, to hear the diſcourſe of ſome
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171201:17"/>perſons thereby to make diſcovery of ſinners, the Reader may obſerve that (paſſing by the miſtake of the Relation) what thereof is true concerning me, is no more then what the ſame diſorderly perſon, now abeting this man, (and the reporter thereof) did (before the diſcovery of his now tranſgreſſions) ſpeak in way of juſtification thereof, as <hi>J. E. doth teſtifie being an eare witneſs.</hi> And whereas the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſuppoſeth ſome fear and miſtruſt of one of theſe perſons, 'tis to be obſerved that accordingly in time it did appear, that is, ſome uncivil behaviour, for which cauſe the perſon was kept out of communion ſome Years: and alſo obſervable it is, that the matter concerning which the Reflection is, was about ſix Years agoe, ſince which time both <hi>Richard Haines</hi> and the other diſorderly perſon, and the now reporter thereof, have had long communion with the Congregation; and yet is it far more evident that a malitious Spirit is the now Author of this Relation; for that long agoe the reporter was told in the Congregation (as alſo before) when there the caſe was propoſed by him, that ſuch a practice as he ſpoke of then (and as is now printed) was not juſtified nor allowed of neither by me, nor any other; <hi>The truth of which, we the Congregation can teſtifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, he declareth that <hi>he had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>med that I did</hi> (to evidence that ſelf intereſt could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> induce me thus to appear againſt him, but rather t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>prehenſion of my duty towards God) makes mention of his reſpects conſiderably large towards me; and thereupon doth (in a way much beneath Chriſtianity, if I may not ſay common humanity) reflectingly ſay theſe words. <hi>Pag.</hi> 35. To wit, <hi>that he did always <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his contributions to one of the Deacons to be diſpoſed thereof according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſcretion; and whether Bell devour'd all, and the poor eate none, and the Idol ignorant (till of late) from whence he had his belly full I know not.</hi> To which <hi>we the perſons (S. L. D. P.) receiving his contributions in in order to the diſpoſing thereof, do hereby teſtifie that as tis true we received ſome thing from him, ſo alſo tis true that according to his direction, the ſame was faithfully diſpoſed of, that is to ſay, partly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:171201:17"/>to the poor, and partly to our brother</hi> Caffyn, <hi>without the leaſt ſhew given for this Reflection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor had he cauſe <hi>to Reflect ingratitude upon me</hi> for that I could, I ſuppoſe, ſhew him the very place where it was ſignified, but had there been ſomewhat really worthy of reproof, the Reader may eaſily conclude that the time, which his contributions now ſpoken of reſpects, was while he was in fellowſhip with us; which if ſo, what may be the Reaſon of theſe publike reflections now, and not the leaſt ſuſpition then ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, I cannot conceive, unleſs to gratifie the Spirit of malice, and vain glory that doth as it were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, blow a Trumpet of what formerly he hath done.</p>
            <p>And whereas he alſo Further ſuggeſteth to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I hold <hi>an errour concerning the Lord Jeſus, and that</hi> Mr. M. <hi>had VVrot ſomething againſt it;</hi> the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is to underſtand that the Title of the Book is but partly repreſented by <hi>Richard Haines,</hi> to wit, <hi>a cure for the Cankering errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> preſented is, <hi>a Cure for the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering errour of the New Eutychians,</hi> which errour at no time was, nor yet is by me beleived, nor do I, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lord Jeſus, nor any other point of Faith, or religious Worſhip, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> then the very ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was believeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>feſſed when he for many Years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> And if by his ſaying, that <hi>I deny that Jeſus Chriſt took his Fleſh of the Virgin Mary,</hi> he means, that the Redemption of Mankind is no more pretious then the Death, and Blood-ſheding of a body of Fleſh, in the fallen Eſtate, under Condemnation for Original ſin, and that was in the beginning of the Earth, as the firſt Man <hi>Adam</hi> was, then do I readily declare my diſſent thereunto, and ſo will (in ſome reſpect) the Author of that Book, (Mr. M.) and moſt others.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:171201:18"/>
            <p>But this I conſent unto, and verily believe, that the true Meſſiah, whom the Father hath ſealed to be the Bleſſed Saviour of the World, was conceived in the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and there took our Nature, and our Form, and ſo was in all points like unto his Brethren, ſin excepted; the Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Son of <hi>David,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be, while the firſt Man was of the Earth, Earthey, the ſecond Man the Lord from Heaven, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47.</p>
            <p>Finally, as it is true that there is many more great ſwelling words of Vanity, proceeding from his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Spirit, unanſwered, as if I were a friend to Popiſh infallability, and had an unlimited power, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable greatneſs, and that knowingly, purpoſedly, and deſignedly I told a lye, without making any mention wherein, together with many other things unworthily, and untruly charged, too large here to repeat, nor do I ſee material cauſe obliging me thereunto; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a cloud of Witneſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his more then ordinary envy, his malitious inſinuations, his bitter expreſſions, his falſe accuſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is manifold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches caſt upon me (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot long ſince were judged by him (as his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Pag.</hi> 2.) moſt faithful moſt worthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> regardleſneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Honour, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> credit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> good of Souls, by this his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> feared <hi>that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeems to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, then let me beg of you the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That you all in Gods fear, whoſe judgments are made manifeſt, take heed of rejecting or ſliting the admonition of Gods people, as this poor man to his great injury hath done.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:171201:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That you do, in the ſence of the great danger, and deplorable condition he ſeems to be in, pray for him, that God may not lay all theſe things to his charge, ſo as hereafter to ſuffer the due deſert of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
